let d and n both be positive integers
this means that we can arrange d dots in
a line
and we can arrange n dots in a line
the theorem we're interested in says
there exists unique integers q and r
with 0 less than or equal to r less than
d satisfying the equality n equals q
times d plus r
to prove the existence of q and r we
start subtracting copies of d from n
as we do this we create a list of
decreasing positive integers
by the least integer principle
of positive integers we know that this
set must have a least element as we see
here where we can no longer subtract off
d
this is going to be the value of r
as we see in the diagram we have
arranged the n dots into an a d by q
array with r dots left over and a line
on top
this means that n equals
q
times d
plus a remainder of r
to prove uniqueness of the pair q and r
let's imagine that we have another pair
q prime and r prime satisfying the same
conditions because these two are equal
we can subtract to see that q prime
times d minus q times d is equal to r
minus r prime
but now because r and r prime are both
between 0 and d their difference is
between negative d and d
this means that q prime times d minus q
times d is a multiple of d that lives
between minus d and d
from this we see that q prime times d
minus q times d must be zero and
consequently that means r minus r prime
must be zero
dividing the second equality by d which
is non-zero shows us that q prime minus
q is zero and r minus r prime is zero
therefore r must be equal to r prime and
q must be equal to q prime this means
that r and q are unique
this concludes our proof of the theorem
known as the division theorem or the
division algorithm
[Music]
you